Guide to the Frank Poole Bevan Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frank Poole Bevan Papers
1914-1971
YCAL MSS 537
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.1
(33 boxes)
The Frank Poole Bevan Papers consist of theater costume designs, set designs, photographs, and other material documenting the work of Frank Poole Bevan. The papers provide evidence of Bevan's career as a designer and faculty member in the Yale School of Drama. The papers illuminate Bevan's creative life and are useful for studying the history of American costume design in the mid twentieth century.
Bevan, Frank Poole, 1903-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Strauss Bevan (Yale, 1940), 1977-1978. Other material came to the library in small quantities from various sources as indicated on individual folders.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Frank Poole Bevan (1903-1976)
Frank Poole Bevan, American costume and set designer, was born on November 9, 1903 to Walter Scott and Daisy May Poole Bevan in Scranton, Pennsylvania. After graduating from Scranton's Central High School (1921), Bevan attended Lafayette College where he received a Bachelor of Arts in 1925.
Bevan enrolled in the Department of Drama in the Yale School of the Fine Arts (later the Yale School of Drama) in roughly 1927. While a student Bevan worked with producer and director George Pierce Baker on Overlords (November 1928) for which he created the costume and set designs. In September 1929 Bevan was appointed Instructor in Costume Design in the Department of Drama. Bevan remained at Yale University throughout his career and held a number of appointments: Assistant Professor, Costume Design (1932-1938), Associate Professor, Costume Design (1938-1950), Associate Professor, Theatrical Design (1950-1956), and Professor, Theatrical Design (1956-1972). In 1930 Bevan studied theatrical design in Germany. Between 1937 and 1940 Bevan worked as a professional designer in New York City where he created costumes for productions such as The Greatest Show on Earth (Playhouse Theatre) and Knickerbocker Holiday (Ethel Barrymore Theatre). Bevan obtained a Master of Fine Arts degree in 1942 from the Yale School of Drama. On December 22, 1944 Bevan married Margaret Strauss Gnau (1904-1978). Margaret ("Margo") Gnau was also a graduate of the Yale School of Drama where she was awarded a Master of Fine Arts in 1940. Bevan worked as a consultant in Hollywood in the summer of 1947 for Joan of Arc starring Ingrid Bergman. In 1956 Bevan was named Associate Dean of the Yale School of Drama, a position he held until 1959. In addition to his teaching responsibilities, Bevan also created costume and set designs for productions at the Yale School of Drama and in New York (including the Metropolitan Opera). Bevan retired in 1971. He died in November 1976.
Scope and Contents
The Frank Poole Bevan Papers consist of costume designs, set designs, photographs, and other material documenting the work of Frank Poole Bevan. The papers provide evidence of Bevan's career as a designer and faculty member in the Yale School of Drama. The papers illuminate Bevan's creative life and are useful for studying the history of American costume design in the mid-twentieth century.
Bevan's designs can be traced from preliminary sketches to final renderings. The papers also include correspondence, fabric swatches, and production photographs, which further reveal the process of transforming Bevan's designs into fully realized costumes and sets. For example, Bevan's costume and set designs for Faust, produced by the Yale Department of Drama in 1949, are captured in final renderings and production photographs. Fabric swatches and Bevan's article for Theatre Arts also give a sense of his creative process and decision-making for Faust. Similarly, correspondence between Bevan and the Metropolitan Opera's Rudolph Bing (general manager) and Horace Armistead (resident designer) regarding Orfeo ed Eurydice offer insight into the stylistic and financial concerns influencing the final costumes, and provide a context for his designs. The papers also include one costume drawing by the designer Robert Edmond Jones, which was owned by Bevan.
The papers chronicle Bevan's education and time at Yale University as both a student and faculty member. Bevan's education is represented by his diplomas and early artwork -- such as a painting "After Bakst" emulating costume designer Leon Bakst -- and his notes on a "final lecture" for 1928. Photographs, a student paper, and retirement tributes reflect Bevan's career as a Professor of Theatrical Design. An album documents an exhibition on "The School of Frank Bevan" at the Wright-Hepburn-Webster Gallery in New York in 1971 in honor of Bevan's retirement.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Costume and Set Designs, 1922-1967. II. Other Artwork, 1932-1970. III. Personal Papers, 1914-1971.
Costume designers -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Set designers -- United States; Theater -- United States; Costume design -- United States; Design drawings -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Costume designers -- United States -- 20th Century; Set designers -- United States -- 20th Century; Bevan, Frank Poole, 1903-1976; Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954; Yale School of Drama
- Costume and Set Designs, 1922-1967; Series I; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title of production.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents Frank Poole Bevan's career as a designer and faculty member with the Yale School of Drama. The bulk of material dates from 1922 to 1967. The series contains Bevan's costume and set designs, ranging from preliminary drawings to final renderings. Fabric swatches, reviews, and production photographs are also part of the series, and help to capture Bevan's creative process and output.
  - Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme
    - Costume designs, gouache and watercolor on paper, 1936
    - Photographs of costume designs with notes, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of production, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Chantecler, costume designs, gouache on paper, undated (Box 1)
  - The Circle of Chalk
    - Photographs of production and Frank Bevan in costume, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of set, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - The Comedy on the Bridge, gouache on paper, 1953
  - Dido and Aeneas, Yale School of Drama
    - Costume designs, watercolor on paper, undated
    - Fabric swatches, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs of production, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Electra, "Klytemnestra," Metropolitan Opera, New York, 1938
  - Faust, Yale School of Drama
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, 1949
    - Set designs, gouache on paper, 1949
    - Fabric swatches, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of costume and set designs, 1949; 2 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of production, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Slides of production, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Photograph negatives, 1949 (Box 2)
    - "Design for 'Faust I,'" by Frank Bevan, Theatre Arts, 1949 July (Box 2)
    - Faust (New York: The Heritage Press), 1930 (Box 2)
      Volume dedicated to Bevan by translator Alice Raphael
  - Frantic Physician, costume designs, gouache and watercolor on paper, 1934; 3
  - The Greatest Show on Earth, Playhouse Theatre, New York
    - Costume designs and photographs, gouache on paper, 1937-1938
    - Reviews, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Henry IV, costume designs, watercolor on paper, 1943
  - Knickerbocker Holiday, Ethel Barrymore Theatre, New York
    - Script, undated (Box 2)
    - Preliminary sketches for costume designs and photograph from production, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Costume designs, watercolor on paper, 1938
    - Reviews, 1938 (Box 2)
  - The Knights of the Round Table
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, 1951
    - Set designs, gouache on paper, 1951
    - Fabric swatches, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs from production, 1951 (Box 2)
  - The Merchant
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, 1939
    - Photographs of costume designs, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Photographs of production, 1939 (Box 2)
  - A Midsummer Night's Dream, costume designs, gouache on paper, 1961-1962; 4
  - Orfeo ed Eurydice, Metropolitan Opera, New York
    - Correspondence with Metropolitan Opera, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, 1954; 2
      Includes fabric swatches
    - Fabric swatches, undated (Box 3)
    - Programs, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Overlords, Yale University Theatre, Yale School of Drama
    - Costume designs, watercolor and pencil on paper, 1928; 5
    - Costume and set designs, watercolor on paper, 1934
  - Prometheus Bound, production photographs, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Psyche, "Psyche: Act 4," watercolor on paper, 1940
  - Rosamunde, notes and costume designs, 1933; 74 (Box 5)
  - Der Rosenkavalier
    - Costume designs, watercolor on paper, 1947
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, undated (Box 3)
    - Photographs of Risë Stevens in costume as Rosenkavalier, undated (Box 3)
  - Salomé, preliminary costume designs, 1938 (Box 3)
  - The Searcher, Yale University Theatre, Yale School of Drama tempera on paper, 1930
  - The Skin of Our Teeth, scripts and clippings, circa 1942; 2 (Box 3)
  - The Taming of the Shrew, costume designs, watercolor on paper, 1955
  - Toad of Toad Hall, costume designs, watercolor on paper, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Venice Preserved
    - Costume designs and photographs of actors in costumes, gouache on paper, 1933; 4 (Box 3)
    - Costume design for Aquilina, gouache on paper, 1933
    - Photographs of actors wearing costumes and of production, 1933 (Box 3)
  - The Winter's Tale, Yale University Theatre, Yale School of Drama
    - Costume designs, gouache on paper, 1931; 2
    - Costume designs and photographs of actors in costume, watercolor on paper, 1931 (Box 4)
    - Photographs of production, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Tin Top, set designs, undated
  - Barcarolle, costume design by Robert Edmond Jones, 1935
    13 x 21 inches
  - Various photographs of actors in costume, stage settings, and Bevan's home, undated (Box 4)
  - Painting "After Bakst" of houri and an attendant, gouache on paper, 1922
  - Costumes for "Fire" and "Water," by William Gleason Adair, 1924 (Box 4)
  - "Lido Beach Costume," gouache on paper, 1926 (Box 4)
  - "Blanca Sanchez Sings Madrid is on the Manzanres," gouache on paper, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Studies for costume designs, 1932-1939; 5
  - Studies for costume designs, 1940-1950; 2
  - Studies for costume designs, 1951-1967
  - Studies for costume designs (largely classical Greek and Roman styles), 1959 (Box 4)
  - Photograph of Bevan in costume as "Carroway Pim" in "Mrs. Pim Passes By", 1928 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Roberta Peters, Risë Stevens, and S. Dillon Ripley, and drawing of Ripley, undated (Box 4)
- Other Artwork, 1932-1970; Series II; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  The series is comprised of a variety of sketches, drawings, and paintings created by Bevan between 1932 and 1970 (note that some material is undated). A large portion of the series consists of drawings of abstracts and clowns. "Miscellaneous drawings" includes some costume designs. One of Bevan's still life paintings portrays his desktop and features one of his designs (signed) alongside fabric samples, paste, measuring tape, and scissors. The series also provides insight into Bevan's artistic work beyond costume design including his interest in Asian art in the 1970s.
  - Sketch of young man, 1932 (Box 6)
  - Various sketches of fashion and plant, 1941-1951 (Box 6)
  - Sketches of nudes, 1946 (Box 6)
  - Sketches of Margaret Strauss Gnau Bevan, 1951-1952 (Box 6)
  - Sketchbook, 1951-1953 (Box 6)
  - Sketchbook (includes watercolors), 1953-1955 (Box 6)
  - Sketchbook of watercolors, undated (Box 6)
  - Painting of person wearing a fedora, undated (Box 6)
  - Painting of masked figure, undated
  - Still life paintings, undated; 8
  - Still lifes and abstracts, undated; 3
  - Asian landscapes and figure studies, 1965-1970; 4
    Watercolor on paper
  - Sketchbooks of Tao figure studies, 1970, undated; 4 (Box 6)
  - Abstract Tao figure studies, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - Flower studies and Asian characters, watercolor on paper, undated
  - Plant studies, watercolor on paper, undated
  - Figure studies, graphite and charcoal on paper, 1948-1950
  - Paintings of dancers and clowns given as Christmas and birthday cards, 1941 and 1954
  - Abstract designs for greeting cards, 1970s; 3 (Box 7)
    Includes cards given by Bevan to Margaret Strauss Bevan
  - Abstract designs, undated; 6 (Box 7)
  - Abstract designs, undated; 8 (Box 8)
  - Abstract designs, undated; 6 (Box 9)
  - Abstract designs, undated
  - Abstract flower designs, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Abstract flower designs, undated; 8 (Box 10)
  - Plaid designs, undated; 4 (Box 11)
  - Drawings of clowns, undated; 4 (Box 11)
  - Drawings of clowns, undated; 11 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous drawings (includes some costume sketches), 1962, undated (Box 12)
- Personal Papers, 1914-1971; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series is comprised of correspondence, photographs, and other documents concerning the personal and professional life of Frank Poole Bevan. Several documents, including diplomas, trace Bevan's student life while at Lafayette College and Yale University. Bevan's work as a lecturer and then faculty member with the Yale School of Drama are reflected in correspondence, printed material, photographs, and other memorabilia. The series also contains some material relating to the Bevan family, such as a family tree, crest, and photographs.
  - Correspondence between Frank Poole Bevan and Frank McMullan (?), 1934-1935 (Box 13)
  - Letter from Thornton Wilder to John Evarts, 1947 January 8 (Box 13)
  - Letter from Frank Poole Bevan to Margaret Strauss Gnau Bevan, 1951 October 16 (Box 13)
  - Various correspondents, 1927-1962 (Box 13)
    Includes a letter of reference from David Belasco written to George Pierce Baker on Bevan's behalf
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1921-1970
  - Yale Alumni Magazine with cartoon of Bevan, 1951 (Box 13)
  - Autograph album presented to Bevan for thirty years of service to the Yale Drama School, circa 1959 (Box 13)
  - Volume of letters presented to Bevan on his retirement as a tribute by the Yale Drama Alumni Association and volume of slides, drawings, and photographs from exhibition "The School of Frank Bevan", 1971; 2 (Box 13)
  - Papers and photographs relating to Bevan's teaching at Yale University, including essay submitted to Bevan by Lee Chin Yang on "Radical Changes of the Chinese Costume," lecture notes, and headshots, 1928-1949; 2 (Box 13)
  - Bevan family genealogy and crest, 1932 (Box 13)
  - Photographs of Frank Bevan, Bevan family, autographed photographs of actors, and clippings, 1914-1954 (Box 13)
- Oversize and Art Storage, 3.67; (20 boxes)
  - Barcarolle costume design by Robert Edmond Jones (Series I), 1935 (Box 14)
  - Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme, costume design (Series I), 1936 (Box 14)
  - The Comedy on the Bridge, costume design (Series I), 1953 (Box 15)
  - Dido and Aeneas, costume design (Series I), undated (Box 15)
  - Electra, "Klytemnestra," Metropolitan Opera (Series I), 1938 (Box 15)
  - Faust, costume designs (Series I), 1949 (Box 16)
  - Faust, set designs (Series I), 1949 (Box 17)
  - Frantic Physician, costume designs (Series I), 1934; 3 (Box 18)
  - The Greatest Show on Earth, costume designs and photographs (Series I), 1937-1938 (Box 18)
  - Henry IV, costume designs (Series I), 1943 (Box 18)
  - Knickerbocker Holiday, costume designs (Series I), 1938 (Box 19)
  - The Knights of the Round Table, costume designs (Series I), 1951 (Box 20)
  - The Knights of the Round Table, set designs (Series I), 1951 (Box 21)
  - The Merchant, costume designs (Series I), 1939 (Box 22)
  - A Midsummer Night's Dream costume designs (Series I), 1961-1962; 4 (Box 23)
  - Orfeo and Eurydice, costume designs (Series I), 1954; 2 (Box 24)
  - Overlords, costume and set designs (Series I), 1934 (Box 24)
  - Psyche, "Psyche: Act 4," costume design (Series I), 1940 (Box 24)
  - Overlords, costume designs (Series I), 1928; 5 (Box 25)
  - Der Rosenkavalier, costume designs (Series I), 1947 (Box 26)
  - The Searcher, costume designs (Series I), 1930 (Box 26)
  - The Taming of the Shrew, costume designs (Series I), 1955 (Box 26)
  - Venice Preserved, costume design for Aquilina (Series I), 1933 (Box 26)
  - The Winter's Tale, costume designs (Series I), 1931; 2 (Box 27)
  - Tin Top, set designs (Series I), undated (Box 28)
  - Studies for costume designs (Series I), 1932-1939; 5 (Box 29)
  - Studies for costume designs (Series I), 1940-1950; 2 (Box 29)
  - Studies for costume designs (Series I), 1951-1967 (Box 29)
  - Painting "After Bakst" of houri and an attendant (Series I), 1922 (Box 29)
  - Still lifes and abstracts (Series II), undated; 3 (Box 29)
  - Painting of masked figure (Series II), undated (Box 30)
  - Still life paintings (Series II), undated; 8 (Box 30)
  - Asian landscapes and figure studies (Series II), 1965-1970; 4 (Box 31)
  - Flower studies and Asian characters, watercolor on paper (Series II), undated (Box 31)
  - Plant studies, watercolor on paper (Series II), undated (Box 31)
  - Paintings of dancers and clowns given as Christmas and birthday cards (Series II), 1941 and 1954 (Box 31)
  - Figure studies, graphite and charcoal on paper (Series II), 1948-1950 (Box 32)
  - Abstract designs (Series II), undated; 3 (Box 32)
  - Diplomas and certificates (Series III), 1921-1970 (Box 33)